Preliminary Inventory to the Roger A. Freeman Papers, 1950-1990
Hoover Institution Archives
- AID TO CHILDREN AND FAMILIES (Box 71-73)
  - AFDC Program
    - Benefits (Box 74)
    - Issues
      - Illegitimacy and birth control (Box 74-75)
      - Absent father
      - Working mothers (Box 75-76)
      - Adoptions and foster care
      - "Suitable" home problem (Box 77)
      - Institutional care
  - Unemployed fathers
  - Child and family welfare programs (Box 77-78)
  - Family assistance program
- OTHER PUBLIC ASSISTANCE PROGRAMS
  - Aid to the blind
  - Aid to the disabled (Box 79)
  - General assistance
  - Medical aid (Box 79-80)
  - Work relief (Box 81)
- OLD AGE INSURANCE (OASDI)
- OTHER PUBLIC WELFARE
  - Unemployment insurance (Box 81-82)
  - Workmen's compensation
  - Veterans
  - Welfare abroad
- THE GROWTH OF AMERICAN GOVERNMENT
  - Foreword (Box 83)
  - Preface, introduction, summary
  - Technical note on statistics, sources, reliability, etc.
  - How Fast is Government Growing? (Box 84-85)
    - Expansion in Government Finance
      - Record of revenues, expenditures, debt in actual $, constant $,% GNP and NI, related to population and prices, per capita data. Tables & graphs 1902-72, 1952-72.
      - Private vs. public activities. Wagner's Law - Galbraith and his followers.
      - Government's role & needs in the XX century (last quarter) Protection and the service state, national priorities
      - Recent trends (Box 86-87)
    - Fiscal trends in war and peace (warfare and welfare)
      - Rates of increase in revenues, expenditures and debt in war periods (1913-22, 1940-44, 1950-53, 1965-69) and peace periods (1902-13, 1922-40, 1944-50, 1953-65, 1969-72)
      - Expenditures for national security (& other war-connected) (Box 87)
      - Expenditures for domestic purposes
      - Tax levels in war and peace periods (federal)
    - Government employment (public servant or bureaucrat?)
      - Is federal employment growing? State & local employment and federal aid.
      - Record 1900-1950 (Fabricant) fed., state-local 1950 (53) 72. Defense & civilian services - relate to population, labor force, private employment, workload, etc. Administrative reorganization. (Box 88)
      - Salary trends (average wages, public & private), unionization, negotiation and strikes
    - Domestic activities of gernment (the Welfare State in Action) (Box 89)
      - Functional breakdown of domestic expenditures
      - Inadaquate services? Examples, Galbraith, etc..
      - Graphs, public and personal consumption, per capita, etc..
      - Rising income, why public goods are scarce, voluntary public activities, alternatives (tax credits)
      - Welfare programs & poverty syndrome (Box 89-92)
      - Actions of 89th to 93rd Congress - outlook
      - Measure of benefits (input-output)
    - Government and security (Box 92)
      - Crime
        - General crime statistics (Box 93)
          - Crime rates and general statistics
          - Cost of crime
          - International comparisons
          - Other
        - Causes of crime and rise in crime rates
          - General
          - Social conditions
          - Laws
          - Courts
          - Police (Box 94)
          - Narcotics
        - Crime and minorities
        - Organized crime
        - Civil disorders
        - Programs for combatting crime (Box 94-95)
          - Role of police
          - Role of courts
          - Legislative programs
          - Retribution, deterrence, and rehabilitation (theories of criminal justice) (Box 96)
          - Other
      - Defense
        - U.S. defensive power, general
          - Overall international & USSR comparisons (Box 96-97)
          - Balance of power or superiority?
          - Strategic deterrent vs. flexible response
          - Arms control and disarmament (Box 98)
          - Joint defense
          - Attitudes of President, Congress, and public
          - Space (Box 99)
          - Other
        - Specific issues on defensive strength
          - Nuclear warfare capability
            - Offensive missiles
            - ABM (Box 99-100)
            - Manned bombers
            - Other
          - Conventional warfare capability
          - TFX, F 15
          - Nuclear Navy
          - Civilian vs. military judgment and control, military-industrial complex
          - Other issues (Box 101)
            - Army, draft vs. voluntary Army
            - Navy
            - Air Force
            - R.O.T.C.
        - Expenditure and cost trends (Box 101-103)
          - Cost trends (constant $,% GNP) (Vietnam & other)
          - Cost effectiveness - PPBS
          - Cost cuts and military strength
          - Economic impact of defense expenditures
        - Dangers to U.S. national security - countries, movements, trends. Time demands on President & Congress.
    - Big Government - Friend or Foe?
      - Benefits, costs & impact of governmental services
      - Standards, measure of benefits, Fiscal policy & growth, purpose of government (American politics tradition) (Box 104)
      - Projections of population & economy, revenue & expenditures
      - Conclusion - trend of expansion & effects on personal liberty. History - growing # and % dependence on government, concentration or power (monopoly), decline of voluntary action, growth of control - examples, regulatory action & guideposts & absence of opposition buy votes, Rome parallel - panem & circenses (Box 105)
  - Facing the Tax Bill (Many Unhappy Returns)
    - The Growth of American Taxation
      - Tax burden & economic growth, what promotes economic growth? (Box 105-106)
      - International comparisons
      - History of fiscal policy (Box 107-108)
        - Federal 1954 cut, 1964 cut
        - 1968 boost, 1969, 1971 cuts, outlook; state and local tax boosts
    - Progressive taxation (redistribution)
      - American tax structure, international comparisons, who pays the taxes?
      - Justification - sacrifice, ability theory, etc., redistribution, Blum-Kalven (Box 109)
      - Effect on incentives, Butters-Break, Soviet tax system
      - Tax awareness
      - Merit & reward in market - social justice?
    - Income taxes
      - Personal
        - General
        - Collections (Box 110)
        - Examptions and deductions
        - Tax compliance (audits, delinquencies, etc.)
        - Withholding
        - International adjustments
        - Tax relief
        - Other
      - Corporate
        - General
        - Rate structure
        - Impact and incidence (Box 111)
        - Economic effects (investment, etc.)
        - Interstate taxation
        - Depreciation allowances
        - Corporate tax shelters
        - Other
      - Loopholes and tax reform
        - General (Box 111-113)
        - Taxing the wealthy (Box 113)
        - Simplification (standard deduction, etc.)
        - Rate structure
        - Nonprofit organizations (churches, foundations, etc.) (Box 114)
        - Oil depletion allowance
        - Capital gains
        - Investment credit
        - Municipal bonds (Box 115)
        - Other (dividend credit, hobby farming, split income - joint return, depreciation, etc.)
        - Tax Reform Act of 1969
        - Tax Reform Act of 1971 (Box 116)
        - Small business tax
    - Consumption taces
      - General retail sales
      - General excise & value added
      - Special excise & sales taxes
      - Customs (Box 117)
    - Property taxes
      - Burden and history
      - Problem areas (uniformity, fractional assessment, unequal distribution, restrictions, etc., land taxation)
    - Employment taxes - Social Security, Unemployment, Workman's Compensation, RR
    - Death, Gift & other taxes
    - Charges & Fees
  - The Shrinking Dollar (Inflation: the Hidden Tax)
    - History of value of $, effects of inflation (who bears the burden?), inflation in other countries, history - political effects (Box 117-118)
    - Demand-pull, inflation (monetary policy)
    - Fiscal policy: budget deficits and the Public Debt, general (Box 119)
      - Size of the deficit and debt
      - Economic effects of the deficit and debt
        - Economic growth
        - Inflation
        - Other
      - Interest costs
      - Debt limit
      - Monatary and fiscal policy (Box 120)
      - Other
    - Cost-push inflation
      - Wages, productivity, government action in labor disputes, competitiveness of U.S. goods, tax load-industry examples (Box 120-121)
        - Construction prices, housing and public works (Box 121)
      - Guideposts, price crackdowns
      - Wage and price control (Box 122)
    - Balance of payments (Box 122-124)
  - Fiscal federalism and centralization of power (Box 124-125)
    - Dispersal of power in the Constitution & centralizing trend
    - The Warren Court
    - Division of revenue sources
    - Division of functional responsibilities (Box 125-126)
    - Fiscal capacity of state & local governments (Box 126)
      - Legal
      - Economic
      - Political (Box 127)
      - Tax immunities
      - Capacity & effort
      - State aid to local governments
    - Federal aid to state & local governments
      - General fiscal aid, tax redistribution, tax credits, in lieu payments (Box 128)
      - State aid to local governments
      - Revenue sharing (Box 129)
      - Tax credits
    - Programmatic grants-in-aid (Box 129-130)
    - Uniform services & centralized control
  - The Services of the Welfare State
    - Social insurance (Box 130)
      - OASI
        - Revenue (Box 131)
        - Expenditures
      - Disability insurance
        - Revenue
        - Expenditures
      - Medical insurance and Medicare (Box 131-133)
        - Revenue
        - Expenditures
      - Unemployment insurance
        - Revenue
        - Expenditures
      - Workmen's Compensation system (Box 134)
        - Revenue
        - Expenditures
      - Private insurance
      - Supplemental security income
    - War on Poverty
      - Definition of poverty
        - Living requirements and living standards (Box 135)
        - Levels of living
        - Cash income
        - Lowest income quintile
      - Number in poverty (Box 136)
        - Income distibution statistics
        - Poverty estimates
        - Progress from poverty (Box 137)
        - Special cases (temporary poor - students, military, etc.)
        - Permanently poor and social and economic mobility
        - Redistributive effects of taxes and expenditures
      - Composition of the poor
        - Population characteristics (overall)
        - Characteristics of the poor
          - Age
          - Race
          - Sex
          - Occupation
          - Education
          - Employment status
          - Skill levels
      - Causes of poverty
        - Poverty cycle (heredity and environment) (Box 138-139)
        - Family breakdown (fertility and income, illegitimacy, etc.) (Box 139)
        - Motivation, effort, and individual responsibility
        - Low intelligence
        - Discrimination
        - Education and skill level
        - Disability
        - Inflation
        - Unemployment
        - Other
      - Programs (Box 140)
        - Economic growth and poverty
        - War on poverty (Box 140-141)
          - Community action programs (Box 141-142)
          - Neighborhood Youth Corps and Youth Conservation Corps
          - Job Corps (Box 142-143)
          - Operation Headstart (Box 143)
          - VISTA (Box 144)
          - Work experience and incentives
          - College work study
          - Adult basic education
          - Rural loans
          - Small business development
          - Aid to migrants
          - Program results - general
          - Problem areas - general
          - Political involvement
          - Legislation (Box 145)
          - Upward Bound
        - Public assistance
          - Aid to families with dependent children
          - Old-age assistance
          - Aid to the blind (Box 146)
          - Aid to the permanently and totally disabled
          - Medical assistance for the aged
          - General assistance
          - Food programs
        - Occupational training (Box 146-147)
          - Public works and work relief (Box 147)
          - Tax credits for training (Box 147-148)
        - Farm programs (Box 148)
        - Housing
        - Education (Box 148-151)
        - Private efforts - jobs and Welfare (Box 151)
        - Income maintenance plans (Box 151-152)
          - Negative income tax (Box 152)
          - Family allowances
          - Guaranteed annual income (Box 152-153)
        - Other (Box 153)
    - Education
      - Elementary and secondary
      - Higher education
    - Highways and other transportation and government regulation
      - Highways
        - Needs
        - Expenditures and construction (including cost estimates)
        - Revenue sources
        - Scandals
      - Railroads (Box 154)
      - Airlines
      - Water transportation (Box 155)
      - Governmental regulation (transportation and other, etc.)
        - History
        - Effects
        - Extent
        - Prospects
        - Federal Department of Transportation
        - Government regulation vs. competition
    - Urban problems and programs
      - Problems, general
        - Economics trends (Box 156)
        - City finances, general
          - Revenues
          - Expenditures
          - Debt
        - City services
          - Police and fire protection
          - Transportation (Box 156-157)
          - Employment
          - Air and water pollution (Box 157-158)
          - Other
        - Population trends, general (Box 159)
          - Magnitude and direction
          - Flight of the middle class
          - Influx of the poor
        - Racial tensions
        - Reapportionment, consolidation, annexation, and home rule
        - Cities (Box 160)
          - New York
          - Washington, D.C.
          - Chicago
          - Los Angeles
          - Detroit
          - San Francisco
          - Other
        - Other references (books, articles, etc.) (Box 161)
      - Programs, general
        - Federal aid, general (Box 161-162)
          - Urban renewal (Box 162)
          - Low-cost housing and rent supplements (Box 163-164)
          - Model cities (Box 164)
          - Welfare
          - Other
        - State aid
        - Other
        - Public control - land use
    - Farm price supports (Box 165)
      - Farm poor
        - Low income farmer
        - Migratory farm worker
      - Migration from the farm
      - Secondary occupations
      - Farm production
        - Productivity
        - Costs of production
        - Processing costs
        - Surplus
      - Price support programs
        - Economic effects
        - Distribution of benefits
        - Cost of program
        - Food for Peace Program
      - Farm prices and competition
    - Depressed areas
      - General statistics (income, unemployment, etc.)
        - Urban
        - Rural
      - Causes of area depression
      - Remedial measures
        - Government action
          - Federal
          - State
          - Local
        - Private efforts
        - Relationship to general economic progress
      - Appalachia
      - Problems in area redevelopment
    - Other public programs (Box 166)
      - Government business enterprises (T.V.A., Post Office, et.) and business subsidies
      - Veterans' programs
      - Natural resources (Box 166-167)
      - Subsidies, loan and credit programs
      - Other
- PUBLIC SCHOOL FINANCE
  - General survey
    - Place and scope of education in the U.S. (history, over-all statistics, goals and accomplishments, length of attendance, illiteracy shortcomings, outlook and problems) (Box 168-169)
    - Population and enrollments (birthrates, age brackets, migration, enrollment, past, present and future projections, dropouts) (Box 169)
    - Investment in education (total expenditures for education, past, present, future for public and private, for elementary and secondary) (Box 170)
      - Economic background, national income and product (other public expenditures, total taxes, consumption expenditures, distribution of responsibility)
      - Effort for education (Box 171)
      - School finance, general (Box 171-172)
      - Return on investment in education (Box 173)
    - General statistics (Box 174)
      - Bureau of the Census - population, enrollment
      - Bureau of the Census - financial
      - Bureau of the Census - housing
      - Bureau of the Census - economic and other
      - Office of Education
      - National Education Association
      - Other (Box 175)
  - School Needs
    - Teachers
      - Total school personnel, labor force, public employees, number of teachers, trends, shortages, division (elementary and secondary classroom and supervisory, etc.) outlook
      - Class size (Box 176)
      - Supply and demand, candidates in training, degrees, causes of shortage, diversification of curriculum, etc. Teachers leaving profession (Box 177)
      - Teacher qualifications, certification standards, tenure credit requirements & methods, summer school credit, emergency (Box 178)
      - Teacher salaries (Box 178-179)
        - Comparisons
        - Scales, sex differences and extra pay
        - Merit pay and administrators (Box 180)
        - Retirement
        - States
        - Standards, outlook, general earning trends
      - Teacher utilization, work schedules, 180 days or 12 month year?
      - Teacher aides
      - Audio-visual and other methods of saving teacher's time, TV and movies, more work load on pupil? Curriculum revision? (Box 181)
      - How to attract more teachers, scholarships, miscellaneous sources of teacher material
      - Case studies of solving teacher shortages
      - Summary outlook:
        - Persons in age brackets
        - Teachers needed under various assumptions
        - Availability
        - Alternatives
    - Buildings
      - Statistics on education construction and other construction, economic implication of faster construction, of classrooms in use, abandoned
      - Surveys of classroom needs and shortages, 1950 status phase, long-range phase, WHCE, etc. (Box 182)
      - Standards, space requirements, obsolescence, double shifts, makeshift quarters, useful life and over-age schools, repair and improvement vs. abandonment (Box 183)
      - Construction costs, comparative; standard plans; prefabs and tempos, potential savings (general school and other indices); school buildings - prefabricated (Box 183-184)
      - Low cost schools (Box 184)
      - Case studies - solved building problems
      - Summary outlook:
        - Construction needs under various assumptions
        - What are the lags and why
    - Results and shortcomings (Box 185)
      - Manpower, shortage of trained personnel, qualification at college entrance
      - Gifted pupils, homework (Box 186)
      - Retarded children, "deprived" children, limits of educability - low IQs (Box 186-187)
      - Failures at Armed Forces tests (Box 188)
      - Illiteracy, retention and drop-out (Box 189)
      - Curriculum (Box 189-190)
        - Congressional material on curriculum
      - Division of classes by ability and accomplishment, promotion
      - Yardsticks of educational accomplishment, voting, economic, report cards, tests, accreditation (Box 190-192)
      - Cost-quality relationships (Box 192-193)
      - Discipline and delinquency
    - Organization, control and management (Box 194)
      - History of school organization in United States and comparison with other countries
      - Separation or integration of schools with local governments, functional disintegration of local government in general
      - Consolidation and reorganization of districts and school units, case stories of unification and local resistance (bedroom-industrial, etc.), comparisons of large and small districts for costs, curriculum, control (Box 195)
    - Special programs (Box 195-196)
      - Vocational education and apprenticeship
      - School lunch program (Box 197)
      - Aid to federally-affected areas, construction
      - Aid to federally-affected areas, operation (Box 198)
      - Transportation and other "housekeeping" functions
      - National Defense Education Act
    - Segregation and integration
      - Cost comparisons between white and colored schools in segregated areas
      - Extent of segregation and trends since court decision: (Box 199-201)
        - Court decisions
        - Legislation
        - Coleman et al.
        - Busing plans
        - Desegregation progress
        - Personal preference and desegregation
        - Public opinion
        - Whites fleeing cities
        - Integration & school violence
    - Trends in nonpublic schools (Box 202)
      - Size and trend of enrollments
      - Class sizes, building programs, teacher shortages
      - Differences in curriculum and results, cost differences
      - Federal (and other governmental) aid (Box 203-204)
      - Vouchers (Box 204)
      - Performance contracts
      - Tax credits (Box 205)
    - Foreign School Systems
      - Expenditures for education and cost of systems per pupil, teachers' salaries, cost of buildings, age of buildings, building standards
      - Time and content standards, curriculum and results
      - Organization, control and finances (Box 205-206)
      - Divisions
        - Great Britain
        - other European countries
        - Soviet Russia
        - other countries
    - Summary of school needs to 1970 (Box 206)
      - Base projections
      - Specific need data under various assumptions
  - Resources for schools - General review
    - Fiscal picture in U.S.A., level of public expenditures, tax burden, deficits (historical, comparative, prospective) (Box 206-207)
    - Schools in the general tax picture - history-outlook
    - Tax systems by level of government (Box 207)
      - General review (Box 208)
      - Federal
      - State (Box 208-210)
      - Local
      - Tax burden by states
      - Tax earmarking (Box 210)
    - Taxes by type
      - General review of revenue sources, historical, comparative, potential (Box 210-211)
      - Shifting and incidence of taxes, tax burden by income, size and economic groups (Box 211)
      - Income taxes
        - Personal income taxes
          - Federal
          - State and local
        - Corporation income taxes
          - Federal
          - State
      - Consumption taxes
        - Gross receipts and turnover taxes
        - Value added taxes
        - Manufacturer's excise taxes
        - Retail sales taxes (Box 212)
          - Federal
          - State
          - Local
        - Custom duties
      - Property taxes
      - Taxes on wealth
    - Other taxes
      - Inheritance, estate and gift taxes
      - Social insurance
      - Gasoline taxes
      - Franchise, license, other charges and taxes
    - Public debt
      - Total indebtedness
      - General obligations and revenue debt, authorities
      - Federal debt
      - State debt
      - Local debt including school debt
      - Interest rates (Box 213)
      - Debt and interest burden by state
    - Tax competition and industrial location
    - Fiscal effort (Box 214)
      - General
      - For schools
    - Fiscal capacity
    - Responsibility for education (general federal-state relationship) (Box 215)
      - Federal constitution, history, court decisions
      - State constitutions, state statutes, court decisions
      - Taxing rights (Box 216)
      - General intergovernmental relations (Box 216-218)
      - History of school support responsibility among levels of government
      - Federal tax immunities and in lieu payments (Box 219)
    - Local sources
      - Property tax (general considerations)
        - History and tax burden
          - Property tax burden (Box 220-221)